Okay.
So thank you to the organizers.
This is this work will be
part of a new book on digital nationalism
that should be out as a Paul Grave pivot
book, probably at the end of next year.
It's a series
that also has Jill Walker at Burges.
Wonderful
seeing ourselves through technology books.
So the website of the Free
Republic of Vertices
invites active participation
from its online visitors.
The country is ostensibly physically
located on the shores of the Danube,
in territory claimed at the border
between Croatia and Serbia.
However, more people have encountered
its quest for official recognition
from the international community
through its online presence, which extends
beyond its official vertices of main
and branches out into social media.
Content created for TikTok, Instagram
and X
that is designed to appeal to so-called
Gen Z audiences
and to reflect the rhetorical
ethos of vertices.
21 year old founder and the current
president of its provisional government,
Daniel Jackson, who is occupied this role
since he was a teenager.
Among the digital paths for reader
interactivity with vertices stated project
as a nation state are visit vertices,
invest vertices, and inhabit vertices.
It is a prominently
positioned option, and those urged
to complete their application
are told that this kind of involvement
in vertices national project will provide,
quote, the ability for you to easily
register and manage a business.
Begin your pathway to citizenship.
Interact with a community of incoming
citizens and business owners.
Receive an E resident card,
allowing you to attend specific
Rhodesian events online and in person
for free, and many other features.
End quote by different tiers
offered by web hosting company.
Applicants could choose
between Resident Basic and Resident Plus.
Of course,
the concept of becoming a national
electronic resident
is not particularly new.
For over a decade,
the well-established and diplomatically
recognized country of Estonia
has offered E residency
to give nonstop access
to Estonian business services
such as company
formation, payment processing and banking
using a smart card
which can be used to sign documents.
Remote workers and investors
in participate in the economy
without a corporeal presence
inside of the country's borders.
As a European Union member and a former
Soviet republic, Estonia has been leading
the world in e-government initiatives
for most of our current century,
branding itself as Estonia
whenever possible.
They introduced a comprehensive program
for national digital ID cards in 2002.
Internet voting in 2005 and residency
in 2014
because of ongoing Russian cyber attacks.
Estonia also deploys digital tools
to defend its national sovereignty.
It's the headquarters
of the NATO Cooperative
Cyber Defense Center of Excellence,
founded in 2008.
It established a data embassy
with Luxembourg in 2017,
and it launched its own Estonian
Defense Forces Cyber Command in 2018.
Many of Estonians innovations
and operating national governance
through mobile devices and distributed
networks have been imported to war
ravaged Ukraine,
and aspects of its virtual residency
project have been imitated
in Lithuania, Portugal and Palau.
An island nation
vulnerable to climate change that risks
becoming permanently inundated by 2050.
Significantly,
this audience of significantly for this
audience of critics
and creators of electronic literature.
The Estonian residency program
was initially aimed at location
independent entrepreneurs such as software
developers and online content creators,
giving digital writers at various
and alternative national identity.
Although Estonia's first Erase it was,
the British journalist Edward Lucas
authored books like Cyber
Phobia and Spycraft rebooted.
Many subsequent
Estonian residents were digital nomads,
taking advantage of the code from anywhere
trend
at the time.
At a time of rising right wing sentiments
against immigration in Estonia,
it remains remarkably uncontroversial
because ethnic, the ethnic
deity of the nations populations, can be
maintained in its geographical territory.
Although residency by initially appear
to be a progressive policy
that materializes the borders
that can obstruct global capitalism,
it maintains the purity of the Estonian
lived environment
and preserve the invisibility
of the non Estonian.
Other.
Residency offers,
in the words of Alex Rivera's narrator
in the film Sleep Dealer.
All the labor without the worker,
end quote.
This 2008 science fiction film
about an imagined dystopian future
takes the kind of this kind of remote work
to an extreme, with Mexican cyber
bursaries working at low wage jobs,
the United States, via virtual reality
enabled robots.
Balaji strain of the network state
has provided a Bible for many of those
aspiring to create small countries,
like the Free Republic of Verdi's,
that also borrow techniques
from Silicon Valley startups.
According to quote, a network
state is a social network
with a moral innovation,
a sense of national consciousness,
a recognized founder, a capacity
for collective action
and in-person level of civility
and integrated cryptocurrency,
a consensual government
limited by a smart social contract.
An archipelago
of crowdfunded physical territories,
a virtual capital, and an online
and an on chain census that provides
a large enough population, income
and real estate footprint
to attain a measure of diplomatic
recognition.
End quote.
Arguing that most nations are small
nations anyway, and that remote work,
digital currency, and smart contracts
have prepared the populace for new norms.
Srinivasan imagines a kind of
built on homo social amity nurtured
online.
Quote the key idea behind
the network state is to populate the land
from the cloud,
and to do so all over the Earth.
Unlike an ideological dissolution
and geographically centralized
legacy state which packs
millions of disputants in one place,
a network state is ideologically aligned
but geographically decentralized.
The people are spread around the world
in clusters of varying size,
but their hearts are all in one place.
End quote.
But the most recent network state
conference held in 2025 representatives
from the governments of El Salvador,
Dubai, Abu Dhabi and Singapore
joined speakers from Ethereum,
Coinbase and Telegram.
Also taking the stage was
a Czech right wing libertarian
politician
who founded the micronation micronation
of the Free Republic of Land in 2015.
Like Vertes,
Libra land is located at a patch of land
that is part of the disputed territory
of the Croatia Serbia border.
During his network state conference
appearance, Tellico publicized
launching a longevity center
in Serbia and a constitutional convention
in the Czech Republic.
He also announced results
from a recent election
in which cryptocurrency billionaire Justin
Sun had been voted in as prime minister,
a position he still holds.
Born in China
and educated in the United States, sun
reportedly has citizenship in Saint Kitts
and Nevis.
A residency card from Malta
and a diplomatic passport from Grenada.
He is known for his ostentatious purchases
of a painting, sculpture
and a conceptual work
by Italian artist Maurizio Catalan.
After the deal for Catalans,
banana duct taped to a wall
was settled at a price
tag over $6 billion.
Sun ate the banana
with gusto as the cameras rolled.
He's given interviews with Sotheby's
to promote NFTs in the art world
as well,
claiming that in the future, quote,
the majority of art will be online,
end quote.
Significantly, it is a lie.
It is alleged
that sun has tried to avoid prosecution
for some of his irregular business
practices
and financial markets by cultivating
a close relationship with U.S.
President Donald Trump and investing
at least $75 million in Trump's meme coin.
The cryptocurrency connection
with micronation founding narratives
and their associated online world building
should be noteworthy for a media studies
audience, although many is less frequently
treated as an object of analysis
and media studies.
Today, monetary currencies and metal paper
and digital forms have been
extremely important in defining the media
studies field as one position to pursue
a broad range of intellectual inquiry
and objects of study.
Marshall McLuhan once
famously devoted an entire chapter
to the subject and understanding media.
His classic text and his classic text
contains a number of other references
to money as a signifier, wealth, a means
of stored value, and a medium of exchange.
As McLuhan notes, all media experiences
structure relations of production
and consumption,
and extends forms of longing and belonging
that are familiar to those who studied
network publics and digital media today.
According to McLuhan, money demonstrates
how, quote, seeing one set of relations
through another set facilitates
how we store and amplify experience.
End quote.
Although this part of McLuhan's
text is often overlooked today,
Canadian mathematician David Aural
brought attention back to
how many is the message when he delivered
the McLuhan lecture in 2015
at transmedia
that focused on quantification, data
and algorithmic
transformations in work, life and play.
How the advent of digital money changes
those
overlapping social regimes of wealth value
in exchange.
Of course, is up for debate.
Noted critic
of electronic literature and Katherine
Hayles, has described money as, quote,
increasingly experienced as informational
patterns stored in computer banks.
End quote.
Just as literary works
and biological identities
appear to have become materialized
as data,
as she argues in bacteria to AI,
these large infrastructures
can be seen as cognitive assemblages
that quote, sense, process, direct,
communicate, and store information flows.
Quote.
In directing her own work of fiction
speculation.
2012 alternative reality game created
with Patrick Goda and Patrick Lemieux.
Hales raises.
Hayles uses historical data
about Wall Street risk, strategizing
strategies, and the occupy movement
and occupy movement resistance tactics
to bring the player's relationship
with capital into question.
As the creative team
writes, quote, gamification often puts
play in the service of labor
and convergence culture
carries inherent complicity
with multinational capitalism.
End quote.
Yet, quote, speculation entails a range
of play forms and transmedia practices
that are not all reducible
to the strategies of finance capitals.
Once playable on the Unity and Mozilla
fireworks platforms,
much of the game is now defunct,
but the question is that
this ARG raises about the lures and hidden
narratives of hyper capitalists.
Abstractions persist.
Although speculation itself
predated today's crypto
markets and influence
scandals, the rhetoric around the Trump
mean coin itself
and the currency can be examined through
the lens of computational multimedia
storytelling and world building.
World Liberty Financial
and its constellation of sycophantic
internet content creators
hyping participatory investment
told the compelling story
about imagined wealth accumulation,
loyalty to the Trump
team, and technological innovation.
Trump himself even proposed
that his crypto might be able to pay off
the $35 trillion national debt in the end
game of this story.
It may be obvious that the language
of cryptocurrency is key
to the political rhetoric of Libra land
founding documents such as the Libra Land
Blockchain White Paper,
which is written in Silicon Valley
technical jargon, rather
than a more traditional lexicon drawn
from a vocabulary of natural rights
or common sense.
The Libra Land blockchain is designed
as a layer one public
public blockchain
governed by the holders of its native
tokens, the Libra land dollar
and Libra Land Merit.
The system also supports non-fungible
tokens and FTS, representing land
and other assets, and implements
a decentralized identity solution.
Unlike Libra Land, the nearby micronation
vertices uses
the conventional euro as its currency.
Although vert is benefited
from a crypto cash infusion.
After the launch of A Verge's coin,
it published a disclaimer
a few months ago about the risks
of investing in cryptocurrency.
Clarified that the coin was neither
endorsed nor official, and explained
the rationale for participating
in more traditional currency markets.
Quote, we have to be very careful
in making sure vertices attractive
for investors,
while also keeping Croatia and Serbia
happy economically and not pulling
investors away from those countries
in favor of lower rates
inverters, for example.
We do not want to risk negatively
affecting the economies of our neighbors.
End quote.
In an
online interview with Domagoj Buttigieg.
He explained how he became involved
in the project
through online conversations
with Daniel Jackson on Discord,
and described his understanding
of the political philosophy and digital
infrastructure of the micronation
with which he now identified as a citizen.
He was eager to differentiate Vertices
cabinet ideologically and generationally
from Leber lands leadership,
even if both initiatives were drawing
from a similar understanding of contested
Balkan territorial claims
and asserting national sovereignty
for homesteads less than 20km apart.
The 28 year old Croatian
electrical engineer and local guide
had become Minister of Foreign Affairs
for vertices
in 2022, and Minister of Defense
and Internet Affairs in 2026.
You can see him above in this picture.
Although Libra Land purports
to be a meritocracy that rewards
civic virtue, its vision for extremely
limited investment and education
and other public goods and its plans
for oligarchical voting schemes
indicate relatively narrow
political commitments
focused on self-interest
and hyper capitalism.
In contrast, Verdi's imagines humanitarian
aid workers as its core population, and
environmental sustainability and military
neutrality is essential national virtues.
While architectural renderings
of Libra Land
depict
expansive and futuristic space age cities.
Those are vertices acknowledge
its vulnerability to the elements
in the floodplain of the Danube
and its need to use repurposed
or local materials, prioritize
eco friendliness
and environmental sustainability,
and promote lifestyles with a low carbon
footprint
that capitalize on passive climate design.
In 2023 has faced an existential crisis
after several settlers,
including President Jackson, were detained
by the Croatian police
and forced by the authorities to surrender
their documents and mobile phones.
According to reports
from the various leadership quote,
they were held at a police station
located near the Hungarian border
for several hours without the freedom
to depart, and subsequently were deported.
After this humiliating encounter, Verdi's
boosters launched a hashtag campaign
to seek to raise visibility
for their cause.
They chose Hashtag Stand with vertices,
a recognizable performative
that mirrored hashtag stand with Ukraine.
Not all online
commentators were sympathetic to the cause
or their narrative of nation founding on
assume Terra Nullius, as they called out
the Eurocentric privilege
of declaring ownership based on a map.
They observed that there were
was another micronation beer to Will
on the border between Egypt
and Sudan that was actually inhabited
by thousands of people.
Although it has been claimed
by a string of outsiders,
a Virginia farmer wanted to crown
his daughter as a Disney style princess.
An Indian businessman craved
a personal kingdom and a Russian DJ.
Inspired by J.R.R.
Tolkien's books,
wanted to transform beer to wheel
into the kingdom of middle earth.
These monarchical projects
weren't really designed to include others
in a shared reality.
However, although some of them drew
on both traditional and new media
narrative techniques,
drawing from scholarship
and speculative fiction, community
based design, and civic liberty,
I might argue that the participatory
online engagement of the
and liberal in their world
building projects merits our attention.
Much as we might analyze
the design elements and gameplay at work
in speculation, given how world building
has been used widely, and multi-platform
works of Ellett, alternate reality games
and locomotive media, we might
imagine how nonfiction
storytelling around national ambitions
might also draw upon similar techniques.
Although electronic literature
often positions itself as a product
of international esthetic production,
we might also ask about
the role of the nation state in shaping
distinct national literatures
that encourage affective investments
in the project of national co fraternity.
Furthermore, although digital culture
was initially assumed to dissolve
the bonds of the state,
we can look at today's digital nationalism
and ask how it differs
from the digital identity
promulgated by so-called print capitalism,
which was described in Benedict
Anderson's Imagined Community Communities,
which argued for the role
of newspapers and novels
in the project of nation building.
Thank you.
And I have to figure out how to stop.
Share. Here we go.
Thank you very much. Excellent